A Guide to the Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock Families 1695(1755-1944)1981
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
There are letters, 1924-1943, from Robert Stevenson Janney to his parents, Abram David Pollock and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney, during his childhood and youth and later during his service in Europe during World War II. On March 5, 1938, he writes from San Francisco, California, following visits to Tokyo and Yokohama, Japan and to Honolulu and Oahu, Hawaii and the voyages between places. He mentions sailing with Taylor Statten and his wife who were on their way home from India where they had been travelling and observing Y. M. C. A. work. On December 8, 1941, while training at Maxwell Field Replacement Center, Montgomery, Alabama, he writes concerning the attitudes of the men receiving the news of the war [the attack on Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, on December 7th], the duplicity of the Japanese government, the immediate effect of guards being doubled or tripled and wearing uniform at all times, and his friends in the 17th Squadron now in Manila. Letters of February 1 & 23 and March 7, 1943, "Some Where in North Africa" mention the climate; the quarters and meals being satisfactory; continuing preparations for training; encouraging news from the Russian front; amusement in the form of movies, a traveling French vaudeville show, and card games; doing some flying; spending all their times on the base; Arab farms and shepherds nearby; and foods for soldiers.
There are letters, 1925-1936, to his aunts, Lilias Janney and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour, concerning his studies, activities and school sports while a student at Princeton University (1934-1936) and a visit to the resort Grandmere in the district of Quebec and playing golf (October 8, 1935). There are letters, 1937-1943, from Janney to his aunts during his youth and later during his service in Europe during World War II. Letters from September 1937 to February 1938 detail his visit to various countries in Europe and to Japan. A September 10, 1937 letter from London, England mentions visits to the British Museum, Houses of Parliament, Tower of London, Madam Tussaud's, St. Paul's, London School of Economics, Oxford University, and Bodleian Library; attending a Russian ballet; and, hearing [George] Campbell Morgan (1863- ) preach at Westminster Chapel. An October 12, 1937 letter from Tours, France describes visits to the Chateau of Chenonceaux, the Chateau of Ambiose, and the interior of a wine-making establishment; mentions visits to Paris, the Louve, the Exposition, the opera (Rigoletto, Carmen, and Fidelio), Versailles, Church of the Madeleline, Arc de Triomphe, the Invaides Palaces, Notre Dame, Church of the Sacre Coeur, Gardens of Luxembourg, Napoleon's tomb, and the Eiffel Tower. A postcard dated November 16, 1937 from Vienna, Austria, concerns a stay in Munich, Germany which ended with a Nazi festival with the presence of German officials, including Adolf Hitler; and visits to Oberammergau and the Bavarian Alps. A postcard dated December 9, 1937 from Naples, Italy mentions visits to Capri via Sorrento and the Blue Grotto and Pompeii and Vesuvius. A postcard [1937] from Florence, Italy mentions staying in Venice for five days and visits to the ancient ruins of Fiesole and an exhibit of Italian thirteenth and fourteenth century art. On December 12, 1937, Janney writes from Nice, France, a lengthy letter giving details of activities and descriptions of places visited while in Europe up to this date. He mentions his traveling companions from Princeton, Boardman Jones of St. Louis and Bradford Cochran of Plainfield, New Jersey. Places visited in Germany included Oberammergau, where they saw the wood carvers' shops and the theatre where the Passion Play is performed; Linderhof, a rococo palace built by Kind Ludwig II of Bavaria; beautiful scenery in Bavarian countryside; and, the top of Germany's highest mountain, the Zugspitze. They took a train trip to Innsbruck and Vienna, Austria, where they visited the Crown Jewels, Imperial Palace, Habsburg crypt, an art gallery, Rigoletto, an exhibition at the Spanish Riding School, a military museum, and the "Blue Danube." He comments on his impressions of South Germany and of Vienna. He details his visits to places in the Italian cities of Venice, Florence, Rome, and Naples. Places mentioned include: Doge's Palace, the Lido, Academia Art Gallery, Church of San Zacharia, Cathedral of San Marco, Church of Santa Maria della Salute, and, a glass-blowing establishment (Venice); Uffizzi Gallery, Church of Santa Croce, Church of San Miniato, Pitti Gallery, a Giotto exhibition, the Cathedral, and, the ruins of Fiesole (Florence); the ruins of the forum and coliseum, the Baths of Diocletian and Caracalla, the Catacombs, National Museum, St. Peter's, Apian Way, Capucina Monastery, Vatican Museum, Sistine Chapel, and Mostra Augustina (Rome); and, Pompeii and Mt. Vesuvius, Capri, and Sorrento (Naples). On January 25, 1938, onboard ship toward Japan, Janney writes about his voyage on the S. S. Potsdam from Genoa, Italy to Manila with stops at Port Said, Egypt; Colombo, Ceylon; and Singapore, Manila. He gives a brief description of volcano eruptions at Stromboli and the straits of Messina in Italy. In Singapore, Malaysia, he made visits to botanical gardens, docks and native quarters. He describes Johore and life there and mentions meeting interesting peoples in Manila, including an Englishman named Hearn. A postcard dated February 1, 1938 from Kyoto, Nippon [Japan] mentions visits to shrines and palaces in Kyoto and Nara. On March 6, 1938, he writes from San Francisco, California about his tour of San Francisco and surrounding country, with visits to Berkeley, Oakland, the University of California, Mt. Tamalpais, Muir Woods, and Chinatown. He mentions hearing Reverend [Charles Rosenbury] Erdman (1866-1960) of Princeton, New Jersey preach. There is a description of Honolulu, Hawaii and mention of his activities. He mentions the voyage on the Empress of Japan from Yokohama with interesting people, including Taylor Statten and his wife, returning from India to observe Y. M. C. A. work; the kindness of the Japanese people; visits to Kobe, Kyoto, Nara, and Tokyo, and, meeting the Hepners, Lutheran missionaries from Virginia. Letters from March - June 1940 concern work with the Japan Reference Library.
Robert Stevenson Janney sent letters to his aunts from October 1941 to December 1943 while training and serving in the United States Army Air Corp. Letters of October 25 and November 3, 1941 are written while training with the 89th Bomb Squadron at Savannah Air Base and mention his application for flying school being favorably received, General [George Catlett] Marshall (1880-1959), plans to go to flying school at Maxwell Field in Montgomery, Alabama, and the beautiful gardens owned by the Henry family. On November 24, 1941, he writes from the Air Corps Replacement Center, Maxwell Field about his activities, including plans to take flying training with seventy other officers; being in the preliminary period designed to give the men their foundation in discipline, drill and general army routine; living arrangements; and, having dinner where at the Baldwin's where Beverley Randolph Tucker of Richmond was a guest. Letters of December 22, 1941 and January 8 and February 17, 1942, written from the Hawthorne School of Aeronautics, mention living arrangements, the routine of army life, his flying progress and first solo ride and acrobatic maneuvers, and the final party at the local cadet club. He writes from Basic Flying School at Shaw Field, Sumter, South Carolina on February 23 and March 16, 1942, mentioning the new facility; their program being full with classes in the morning and flying the afternoon; a new type of plane more complicated, faster and more powerful; restrictions on discussions of training; and, a dance for the cadets in Hartsville. Letters of May 3 and June 6, 1942, written from Moody Field, Valdosta, Georgia, mention the trip from Sumter to Valdosta; advanced planes; having an x-card for gas rationing; Cecil Thompson of the First Presbyterian Church; bad weather delaying flying; doing some night flying, local and cross-country, in addition to regular day time flying and ground school; and a weekend trip to Montgomery, Alabama. On July 19, 1942, Janney writes while with the 465th Bomb Squad at Key Field, Meridian, Mississippi, mentioning that they are learning to fly a new type of plane, the Douglas Boston bomber (DB-7), which is fast and maneuverable and chiefly used against ground forces and that they are being readied for combat duty. Janney was with the 465th Bomb Squadron until December 1942. On September 21, 1942 he writes that the maneuvers were a valuable experience and that they took place along the Sabine River, the boundary between Louisiana and Texas and that they used the A-20-B. Postcards, September to November 1942, from bases in Louisiana, mention his new position as squadron operations officer, scheduling flights, the 27th Bomb Group doing maneuvers in the region, living quarters, athletic facilities, flying facilities, and night flying. On December 27, 1942, Janney writes while with the 27th Bomb Group at Harding Field, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, stating that training is proceeding at an increased rate and that he was presented with a Swiss wristwatch from the men in his squadron upon his retirement as their commanding officer. In a letter of January 18, 1943, en route to North Africa, Air Base, Natal, Brazil, he describes a quaint town of about 200,000, with the natives a mixture of Portugese, Indian and African-American strains. On March 21, 1943, with the 27th Bomb Group, somewhere in North Africa, he writes about their recreation of volleyball and baseball; the Arabs and French in the area; a diet of eggs, oranges and tangerines; Bill Clifford of Loudoun County being there; and, good living conditions. On April 15, 1943, with the 47th Bomb Group, somewhere in North Africa, he writes about his transfer to another organization, with other fellow pilots from the old group and describes a visit to Algiers. On May 24 and June 20, 1943, with the 84th Bomb Squadron, 47th Bomb Group, he writes about seeing many prisoners on his trips to the battle area; some places being torn up and strewn with equipment while some fields are under cultivation; land mines left by the Germans; his new living arrangements; Walter Janney, Jr. being around; and, the squadrons being reviewed by a high British official. There is V-mail dating from July through December 1943 which mention living in a British Officers' quarters and a visit to Constantine, Algeria where Bastille Day was celebrated with parades and patriotic ceremonies (July 25, 1943); being at a British base and the British putting to use what they learned about managing in the field (August 4, 1943); visits to Mt. Etna, Catania and other places as well as Syracuse, Augusta and the straits of Messina and the inhabitants of Sicily, Italy (September 5, 1943); a visit to the Isle of Capri (October 4, 1943); and, a visit to Naples, Italy (November 1, 1943).
Correspondence and Papers of the Gilmour, Janney and Pollock families
Papers of the Gilmour, Janney and Pollock families include correspondence and papers of members of these families of Loudoun County. Folders are arranged in groups by specific individuals or couples: Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour (1886- ); Abram David Pollock Janney (1880- ) and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney; Charles Phillips Janney (1839-1925) and Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney ( -1908); John Janney, Jr. (1878-1967); Lilias Janney (1874- ); Nathaniel Ellicott Janney (1813-1848); Thomas Gordon Janney (1870- ); and, Lily Pollock.
Letters, 1897-1946, to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour cover a variety of topics. On June 19, 1897, John R. Sampson, principal, Pantops Academy, Charlottesville, to writes A. D. P. Gilmour concerning his favorable decision to hire Gilmour for a vacancy in the mathematical department. There is an essay, October 27, 1898, describing "The Island of Canna" and "The Cave at Eigg" in Scotland. On October 3, 1939, Carrie Lena Moffett refers to her visit to Shanghai, China, mentioning news of the Moffetts and others, the hospital and the Refugee Hospital in Shanghai, the need for Chinese technicians in Kiangyin, and Ruth Worth teaching technicians at the Refugee Hospital. On December 30, 1939, Peter Mao, Boys' Department, Y. M. C. A., Shanghai, writes concerning missionary and education work in Kiangyin and a celebration in honor of three of their missionaries, Lacy L. Little, Andrew Allison, and Kathryne L. Thompson. On January 30, 1940, Charles W. Worth, Hangchow Christian College, Hangchow, Che., China, writes about the uncertain and confusing political situation, the effects of the Treaty lapse, poverty throughout the occupied areas, and the amount of relief work. Letters, 1844, from W[illiam]; H[ammond] Milton (1868- ) and Virginia Lee Milton touch upon his early ministry, [Archibald Joseph] Cronin's The Keys of the Kingdom and Evelyn Underhill's Worship, and, the death of the Gilmour's nephew [Robert Stevenson Janney]. On July 10, 1944, J[oseph Gr⥧oire] de Roulhac Hamilton (1878-1961), The Library, University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill, encloses a brochure on the University's "A National Southern Collection" and refers to the Pollock diary. A letter of May 28, 1946, from Brooks Palmer (1900?- 1974) of New York, refers to Daniel Monroe, a Massachusetts clock maker.
Letters, 1908-1965, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour, chiefly pertain to news of family and friends in Leesburg, Virginia. Letters of 1935 refer mostly to her engagement to A. D. P. Gilmour. Other items of interest are mentioned. There are letters (May 16, 1934; October 14, 1935, March 2 & 17, 1936; and, January 22, 1955) from Reverend James Shannon Montgomery, Minister of the Leesburg Presbyterian Church, chiefly concerning church matters and news of Leesburg and its inhabitants. In 1934, Montgomery also mentions a visit to Westfield, New Jersey and Princeton, a meeting with William K. McKinney and his request for him to talk to Robert [Stevenson Janney] about his interest in the ministry, and describes the reunion held at Princeton. In 1955, Montgomery writes from a retirement community, Olds Hall, Daytona Beach, Florida, that he is still opposed to the Church Union movement, and about religious insights, the division of the Presbytery of St. Johns, and the rapid increase of the Florida population. There is a letter, January 4, 1935, from Lily H[eth Davis] Dabney (1875-1973) at the University of Virginia. There are letters, January 1935, from W[illiam] Sinclair Bowen (1867-1951), Cleveland, Ohio and Rachel [McMasters] M[iller] Hunt (1882-1963), Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, about her engagement. There are letters (January 9, 1935; [post 1943] August 7) from Edward Griffith Dodson (1884-1969), Clerk, Virginia House of Delegates, concerning personal matters. On January 17, 1935, Harrison Williams (1873-1953 ?), Washington, D. C., writes as president of the Thomas Balch Library concerning her resignation of the chairmanship of the Grounds Committee and the work so far accomplished. There is a letter, February 8, 1935, from Daisy H[aywood] Moseley (1892- ) of Glen Ridge, New Jersey. There is a letter, February 13, 1935, from Hugh Chaplin (1887-1973) of New York mentioning a Chinese meal with a group of old Chinese friends. On March 14, 1935, Cazenove G[ardner] Lee, Jr., Washington, D. C., writes about the progress at "Stratford" and about the Lee Society. There are two letters (March 25 and May 8, 1935) from former University of Virginia student, Edmund J[ennings] Lee (1877- ), Rector, Chatham Hall, Chatham, Virginia, concerning personal matters and mentioning his wife, Lucy. There is a letter, Mary 24, 1935, from "Josey" in Hwai-an, Ku, China, concerning mission work and religious and educational work in that area. A September 23, 1935 letter from "Betty" in Jersey, Channel Islands, mentions the feeling of war in Europe, especially Italy, and a visit to London, and describes Jersey and its inhabitants. There is a December 22, 1935 letter from Constance Cary Harrison of "Belvoir," Fauquier County. Other letters of interest to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour are from Ada H. Wright, a missionary in Japan and Australia. Letters of January 7 & 17, 1935, from Kumamoto, Ki_shi_, S. Japan, mention mission work for local people, a visit to the Government Leper Asylum, St. Timothy's Church in Tokyo, work with the lepers in the Loo Choo Islands and at the Government Leper Asylum and describes a Christmas celebration. A letter from the same place on February 16, 1935 mentions the engagement and an addition to their hospital. A letter, February 2, 1944, from Wright in Guildford, Perth, Western Australia, mentions an auxiliary for the Mission to Lepers in Perth. A letter, August 17, 1939, from "Jessie" at Golf Hotel, Woodhall Spa., [England], contains a description of the village of Woodhall, and mentions the King and Queen of England [King George VI and Queen Elizabeth] touring America, offering "Rosemont" for housing evacuated children, and Germany blindly following Hitler. On May 20, 1941, Robert E. Peyton, Jr., Richmond, writes concerning the negative effect of the war in Europe on the prosperity of apple orchards in Virginia. There are also letters from the summer of 1944 expressing sympathy over the death of the Gilmour's nephew, Robert Stevenson Janney. There are letters (September 1, October 11, 1958; December 28, 1960; and, December 18, 1961) from Stewart Couper of Midlothian and Angus, Scotland, concerning religion, church matters, and conditions and life in Scotland. An undated letter, February 20, from Hetty Harrison, Hay-Adams House, Washington, D. C. discusses gardening and several Virginia nurseries, and mentions Constance Cary Harrison. An undated letter, March 22, from "cousin Lily" in Paris, France, mentions travel around Nice and Paris, France, and gives her opinion of Paris.
Letters, 1929-1964, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from her brother, John Janney, Jr., touch upon legal, political, and religious concerns as well as events in Pioche, Nevada. Letters of March 22 and April 5,1935, on "American Society of Practical Economists" letterhead, mention Janney being one of the speakers at a meeting of the Foreign Policy Association and comment on the financial depression in the county and on the Congressmen from North Carolina "playing in with the international bankers by letting them manage currencies..." The latter one comments at length on senators and congressmen from North Carolina being blind to "this monetary situation" and thus not "lending any substantial cooperation to any effort in the Congress to save this great nation from its present tragic plight..." and mentions control of the value of the properties of this nation, the manipulation of private banking interests, and other national financial interests. A March 15, 1936 letter discusses Jewish and Christian sermons in his area and comments on the modern revisions to the sermons. On May 8, 1936, Janney is "On Board Steamship" traveling through a canal. A letter of October 6, 1950 relays personal and legal news. On Febraury 20, 1958, Janney mentions Governor [J. Lindsay] Almond's speech [on segregation] and comments on the conditions in Virginia. Letters of January 9 and February 15, 1959 comments at length on "Massive Resistance" in Virginia as well as on Governor Almond usurping the rights of the legislature. On April 29, 1959, Janney writes that he has much work since he took on the job of Virginia political deficiencies. A November 9, 1959 letter discusses an agreement on the family farm and a controversy with the bank and the life tenant. There is a copy of a letter, December 13, 1962, from Janney to George S. Montgomery, concerning a Pioche, Nevada court case involving Dolman and Company and its effect on the Pioche Mines Company. A July 7, 1964 letter on "Pioche Mines Consolidates, Inc." letterhead also discusses the Dolman-Lee case as well as other legal work.
Letters, 1908-1940, n.d., to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from her sister, Lilias Janney, chiefly discuss family and friends and events in Leesburg, Virginia. On February 1, 1908, she writes from Los Angeles, California concerning visits to Los Angeles and Pasadena, mentioning the actions taken in locating a room and meeting a woman who is a Christian Scientist and a practitioner. On April 21, 1916, she writes from Yokohama, Japan, discussing her trip to Kamakura, with a visit to a "Tea House" and to the home of [Inazao] Nitobae (1862-1933) and his wife [Mary Patterson Elkinton] Nitobae, and comments on a procession of the Emperor and Empress and their court. Letters of June 1929 refer to the death of Leon Fry while schooling a horse, her nephew, Robert [Stevenson Janney] going to Camp [Ahmeck, Algonquin Park], Ontario, and Cary Langhorne entertaining the Garden Club. One letter in June is from "The Monticello," Charlottesville, where she has visited "Monticello," Michie Tavern, Farmington Country Club, and the University of Virginia. A letter, ca. January 1935, from the Acorn Club, Philadelphia, describes the attendance of Anne [Janney's] recital at the Hotel Barclay ballroom and includes a newspaper clipping. Letters of February 21 and 27, 1935, from Plainfield, New Jersey, mention a Bokara man who sells rugs, including Persians and Orientals and a visit with her nephew, Robert [Stevenson Janney], at Princeton University and to Westminster School. In a letter, ca. February 1935, she writes about her visit to New York and hearing [Ignaz] Friedman (1882-1948) who, she feels, is in the same class as [Ignace Jan] Paderewski (1860-1941) and going to the Metropolitan Museum. A letter of April 29, 1935 mentions Caz[enove Gardner] Lee. On June 17, 1935, she writes news of the Garden Club, mentioning the medal given to [John Davison] Rockefeller (1874-1960) for the Williamsburg Palace gardens. On June 20, 1935, she mentions the Massanetta Festival in July and being chairman of the "Open Air" Music Committee. A September 20, 1935 letter gives news of Robert Heston who has been cooking at a Catholic institution and a riding club. A September 28, 1935 letter refers to the management of family property rented to the Gallehers and the possible offer to sale to them. On November 26, 1935, she mentions meeting Mrs. [John Stewart ?] Battle [Mary Jane (Lipscomb) Battle ?] at a tea. A letter, ca. January 1936, mentions the death of "Harry" [Henry B. Rust]. From January 21 until February 12, 1936, Lilias writes from Hamilton, Bermuda. She discusses her arrival in the unique and beautiful town of Hamilton; activities including the service for the King at the Cathedral, a visit to Warwick Parish Church; activities with the Pattons; a train trip to Somerset; [Henry] Van Dyke (1852-1933) and his "poetic spirit"; guest houses and shopping and plans to go sailing. Letters of March and April 1936 discuss life in Leesburg. There are numerous undated letters from Lilias Janney. In a February 5th letter, she mentions seeing Mary of Scotland with Helen Hayes (1900-1993) as Mary. In a May 5th letter, she mentions having tea at the Pattons, stating that "Old Mrs. Patton is quite the Grande Dame...Mr. & Mrs. George Patton being quite important people here. He is in Parliament & her niece married Lord Kitchener's nephew & they own an island."